Okay, moving on to nephrotic syndrome.
These are glomerular disorders,
the hallmark of which is proteinuria,
and of course, that proteinuria needs to be greater
than 3.5 grams per day.
Now, the major protein in the blood
and the major protein that is lost
in this particular group of disorders is albumin,
and so the patients become hypoalbuminemic.
Now, of course, albumin plays an important role
in maintaining the oncotic pressure of the blood,
so a loss of albumin would result
in a decreased oncotic pressure,
and the decreased oncotic pressure would result
in increased fluid within the tissue space or edema,
and so the consequence of the hypoalbuminemia will be edema.
In addition, the patients will lose gamma globulin,
which is another important protein within the blood,
and the loss of gamma globulin
will result in hypogammal globulinemia,
which, of course, then will increase the risk of infection.
In addition, the patients will develop
a hypercoagulable state.
Now, the reason that they develop a hypercoagulable state
is that they preferentially lose antithrombin 3.
So if they lose antithrombin 3,
they've lost one of their anticoagulant proteins,
and so they become procoagulable.
Remember that antithrombin 3 plays the important role
of breaking up thrombin,
and also of destroying coagulation factors
so that you can't produce thrombin.
So it is an anticoagulant protein,
and if you lose it, you're gonna get hypercoagulable.
And finally, the patients are going to have hyperlipidemia
and hypercholesterolemia.
Now, the way I think about this
is because there's loss of so much protein from the blood,
the blood becomes, quote-unquote, relatively thin,
and so the liver reacts by throwing excess fat
into the blood to sort of beef it up a little bit.
And it's a funny way of thinking about it, but it works.
And so, therefore, the patients become hyperlipidemic
and hypercholesterolemic, and this is important.
Board examiners like to ask about this as well.
The first of the nephrotic syndromes
is minimal change disease, this is the most common cause
of nephrotic syndrome in children.
It's usually idiopathic.
That's not anything special because the vast majority
of nephrotic syndromes are usually idiopathic.
However, it can be associated with Hodgkin's lymphoma,
and that's super high yield.
In order to understand this association,
let's go back and remind ourselves
that the glomerular filtration barrier contains three layers.
The first is the endothelial cell,
sitting on top of a basement membrane, upon which sits
the podocytes, or I should say more particularly,
the foot processes of the podocytes.
Of course, this is also called, this layer of foot processes
is also called the epithelial cells.
And so you can think of it as endothelial cells
sitting on top of a basement membrane,
upon which sit the epithelial cells,
or the foot processes of the podocytes.
Now, this tri-layer forms the filtration barrier
for the glomerulus into the tubular space.
In minimal change disease, you lose the foot processes.
So if this is the endothelial cells here,
you get effacement of the foot processes,
with this being normal,
and then flattening of the foot processes here
being abnormal.
Now, what causes the effacement of the foot processes
in this particular disorder is the production of cytokines.
And so cytokines mediate this particular damage
to the foot processes.
Now, recall that in patients with Hodgkin's lymphoma,
you get massive overproduction of cytokines
by the Reed-Sternberg cells.
In fact, that's why patients with Hodgkin's lymphoma
can often present with B symptoms,
because the cytokines get released into the blood,
giving you fever, chills, night sweats, et cetera.
And so in the same way, these cytokines can hit the kidney,
and when they hit the glomerular filtration barrier,
they can knock out the podocytes, resulting
in minimal change disease.
Now, regardless of the cause, whether it be idiopathic
or associated with Hodgkin's lymphoma,
the key findings in minimal change disease
will be normal glomeruli on the H&E stain.
You might see a little bit of lipid
within the proximal tubular cell.
However, the hallmark of this disease
is normal glomeruli on H&E stain.
The key finding, however, is that on EM,
the patients will have effacement of the foot processes,
as I've already illustrated in our diagram.
Now, it's important to note that this disorder
is not driven by the deposition of immune complexes,
and so therefore, the immunofluorescence
will be negative.
The immunofluorescence is basically most useful
when you have immune complex deposits,
and so you won't really see anything specific
on the immunofluorescence.
Now, another important thing about minimal change disease
is that you get selective proteinuria.
You do lose albumin, however,
you do not lose immunoglobulin.
Otherwise stated, the change is so minimal
that the only protein that is lost is albumin.
This has an excellent response to steroids,
and again, that's because the damage
is mediated by cytokines.
So if you give steroids and you knock out the ability
to produce cytokines, that would then result,
of course, in an excellent response.
And it's important to note that this is really
the only nephrotic syndrome in which you get
an excellent response to treatment.
This is a histologic image of a glomerulus
taken from a patient with minimal change disease.
Of course, in minimal change disease on H and E,
the glomerulus should look normal.
And this basically is a normal glomerulus,
but it gives us an opportunity to review
some normal histology as well.
Now, recall that the outer capsule here
is called Bowman's capsule.
This is called Bowman's space,
and then you actually have the glomerulus
sitting here in the middle.
Now, the glomerulus is divided into lobules,
and that's the functional unit of the glomerulus,
so you've got all these lobules here.
And remember that the lobules are held together by mesangial cells,
and so this pink region here represents the mesangium.
And the mesangium holds together these capillary loops
upon which the filtration actually occurs.
And, of course, the filtration barrier
should be very thin and delicate.
And notice that the wall here of the capillaries,
as I'm highlighting here, is very thin and delicate.
And so this is a normal glomerulus.
Now, on EM, which is where you're going to find the key changes
with minimal change disease, you're going to get effacement
of the foot processes, as I'm marking here.
Again, these are red blood cells,
so this would be the blood vessel.
Here is the endothelial cells here.
This is the basement membrane.
And then this is where the foot processes should be.
However, you can clearly see that the foot processes
are effaced or flattened.
And again, that's the hallmark of minimal change disease.
The next disorder is focal segmental glomerulus sclerosis.
This is the most common cause of nephrotic syndrome
in Hispanics and African Americans.
Again, as with most nephrotic syndromes,
it's usually idiopathic.
However, it can be associated with HIV,
heroin use, or sickle cell disease.
This is very high yield.
Now, let me just remind you that if you have a patient
on an examination or in the clinics,
and they have HIV and then develop nephrotic syndrome,
the nephrotic syndrome that they have
is focal segmental glomerulus sclerosis.
Similarly, the most common cause of nephrotic syndrome
in heroin users is going to be
focal segmental glomerulus sclerosis.
And if you have a sickle cell patient
and they develop nephrotic syndrome,
again, you're gonna think about
focal segmental glomerulus sclerosis.
Now, the name focal segmental glomerulus sclerosis
actually gives away what we're going to see
in this particular disorder.
The words glomerulus sclerosis imply
that we're going to see a dense pink deposition
of collagen within the glomerulus.
In addition, this deposition will be segmental.
And what segmental means is that if you were to look
at the circle of the glomerulus,
it would only involve one segment of the glomerulus,
whereas other segments of the glomerulus would be normal.
Finally, the word focal means that you will have involvement
of only some of the glomeruli within the kidney.
And so, for example, if there were three glomeruli
within the kidney, maybe only one would be involved.
And, of course, there aren't three glomeruli in the kidney,
but I'm just simply using that as an example.
So, again, focal, one out of three, for example.
Segmental, the one that is involved,
only part of the globe or part of that circle
is actually involved.
And what's the lesion?
Pink sclerosis within the glomerulus on H and E.
Now, in this particular disorder, you get effacement
of the foot processes on EM.
Now, here's how I think about this.
What you need to remember is that when you have a patient
with minimal change disease, the vast majority
of those patients respond to steroids.
However, if you were to give a patient with minimal change
disease steroids and they didn't respond,
what they would progress to would be focal segmental
glomerulosclerosis.
So, it's sort of the progression of what happens
in minimal change disease were the disease
to not respond to steroids.
And so that helps me to remember that you're going to see
the exact same pathology on EM,
which is that you'll see effacement of the foot processes.
Now, in this disorder, it's not driven
by immune complex deposition.
And therefore, because it's not driven
by immune complex deposition,
you really won't see anything significant
on immunofluorescence.
You can see some nonspecific findings,
but for your purposes of grasping this material
for examinations and a general understanding,
you're not going to really see anything specific
on immunofluorescence.
Okay, here's a picture of focal segmental
glomerulosclerosis.
I've shown you the one involved glomerulus.
And so here's the globe of the glomerulus.
You can clearly see that there's sclerosis
within the glomerulus.
However, it's segmental.
Here it's normal.
And here you have sclerosis.
Now, of course, focal segmental glomerulosclerosis
is going to have a poor response to steroids.
The vast majority of nephrotic syndromes,
except minimal change disease,
usually don't respond to treatment.
And so it'll progress to chronic renal failure.
The next of the nephrotic syndromes
is membranous nephropathy.
Now, this is the most common cause
of nephrotic syndrome in Caucasian adults.
And that's particularly high yield.
It's usually idiopathic.
But of course, that's nothing special
because nephrotic syndromes are usually idiopathic.
However, it can be associated with hepatitis B or C,
solid tumors, lupus, or some drugs.
Now lupus is particularly important here.
Let me just remind you that patients with lupus,
the most common cause of death is renal failure.
And the most common disorder that they get within the kidney
is actually a nephritic syndrome
called diffuse proliferative glomerulonephritis.
However, lupus patients can also present
with nephrotic syndrome.
And if they present with nephrotic syndrome,
then the nephrotic syndrome that they develop
is membranous nephropathy.
And that's very high yield for board examinations.
So it is important to note these associations.
For example, hepatitis B and C, solid tumors, lupus, drugs, etc.
Now in membranous nephropathy,
the key finding is actually given away by the name membranous.
So what's going to happen is you're going to get
thick glomerular basement membranes on H and E.
So that filtration barrier that we normally would see on H and E
to be thin and delicate is going to become thick.
And so let me show you an image of that
just to highlight this principle.
Now here is a glomerulus.
And when you look at this glomerulus,
what you can recognize is that the glomerular filtration membrane
has become particularly thick.
And so hence, we give it the name membranous nephropathy
because that membrane has become thick.
Now, you can ask the question,
why did the membrane become thick?
And in the disorder membranous nephropathy,
the key problem is that you have immune complex deposition.
I'll give you a little bit of a hint.
Any disease that has the word membranous in it,
and there's only two, membranous and membranoproliferative,
which is going to be the next disorder
that we're going to cover,
in all of those cases, you get thickening of the membrane,
and the thickening of the membrane
is due to immune complex deposition.
All right, so that's going to be a general theme.
And I'll highlight that one more time as we go along.
Now, in this particular case,
once you have immune complex deposition,
then you should know that the immunofluorescence
is going to be granular.
This is important to highlight, so let me illustrate it.
Here again, you've got the endothelial cell,
and the endothelial cell sits on the basement membrane,
and upon that sits the podocyte.
Now, what's going to happen in this disorder
is that we are going to get immune complex deposition
at the level of the podocyte.
So it will be right underneath the podocyte,
or right under the epithelial cell,
and so it's also called subepithelial.
Now, a few important things.
Number one, these deposits will be detectable
by immunofluorescence.
And the immunofluorescence is going to light up
the little grains of deposit,
or the little circular deposits,
which basically is then going to produce a granular,
or a grainy immunofluorescence.
At the same time, the other point to note
is that when these deposits are sitting
underneath the epithelial cell, or the podocyte,
the podocyte will respond by trying to lay down
additional basement membrane.
Basically, epithelial cells need to sit on basement membrane,
and they don't like to be kicked off
of their basement membrane by these deposits.
Now, as they lay down additional basement membrane,
what's going to happen is you're going to generate
a dome over the deposit.
And then, let's pretend there's another deposit here.
You're going to generate another dome over that deposit.
And in between the dome, you're going to create these spikes.
And so you get this spike and dome,
spike and dome appearance on EM.
And that's a classic description of the EM
of membranous nephropathy.
Now, let's go back and just see what we say here in the notes.
So membranous nephropathy is called membranous
because you get thick glomerular basement membranes on H and E.
Of course, anytime you have the word membranous in the name
of the disorder when we're studying these disorders,
it's going to be due to immune complex deposition.
The immune complex deposition is going to give us a granular
immunofluorescence because we're going to light up each of those
little grainy immune complexes.
Now, of course, because this is subepithelial and this disorder
is characterized by subepithelial deposits,
we're going to generate a spike and dome appearance
on the electron microscopy.
Here is the H and E image that I've already shown you.
And the key problem here is that you've got thickening
of this glomerular filtration barrier
or thickening of the membrane.
When you look at this on immunofluorescence,
what you're going to see is this grainy
or granular immunofluorescence.
And so just focus here for a minute.
Can you appreciate all the little dots that are going,
that are being put together in order to create
this immunofluorescence pattern?
Again, that's the granular immunofluorescence.
And granular immunofluorescence equals
immune complex deposition problem.
It tells you that there is immune complex
depositing within that membrane.
Of course, you would then do EM to try to localize
where the immune complex is.
And in this particular case, the immune complex
is right underneath the podocyte.
And it's kicking off the podocyte.
Now, of course, when the podocyte is separated
from its basement membrane, it's not going to be happy about that.
And so it's going to lay down new basement membrane.
And when it lays down new basement membrane,
you're going to create these domes and then a spike
and then another dome and then another dome.
And this would be the spike here in between the deposits.
So again, domes on top of the deposits and spikes in between.
The next nephrotic syndrome is membranoproliferative
glomerulonephritis.
The term membrano tells you that you're going to get thickening
of that capillary membrane on H and E.
And of course, whenever you have the word membrano
when you have thickening of the capillary membrane,
it's going to be due to immune complex deposition,
as I've already explained.
And of course, whenever you have immune complex deposition,
you're going to have a granular immunofluorescence.
Now, in addition, notice that we have the word proliferative here.
And what proliferative means is that the mesangial cell
that's holding together all of those capillary loops,
the cytoplasm of the mesangial cell is going to proliferate
and it's going to, it's going to separate the deposit,
creating a classic tram track appearance.
Let's illustrate this.
So here you have the endothelial cell.
And of course, the endothelial cell sits
on top of basement membrane.
And then above that, you've got the foot processes
of the podocytes.
Now in this particular disorder,
let's imagine that you get a immune complex deposit.
And the immune complex deposit in membranoproliferative
can be underneath the endothelium or it can be
in the basement membrane.
Let's put it here underneath the endothelium
for the time being.
Now what's going to happen is here is the mesangial cell
holding together the capillary.
And when the mesangial cell sees this deposit,
it will proliferate its cytoplasm and basically cut
through the middle of that deposit.
When it cuts through the middle of the deposit,
it's going to create or separate the deposit into two pieces.
And these two pieces are going to look like a tram track.
You know, two lines which basically form a track.
And so that's why I say here in your notes
that it's going to have a classic tram track appearance.
Now this is the easiest thing to remember
for board examinations.
Because the name tells you, right,
that you've got a membrane,
and that there's going to be proliferation
of the mesangial cells, hence the word proliferative.
And that proliferation of the cytoplasm of the mesangium
is going to cut the deposit in half,
creating two lines, which is a tram track.
So it's a giveaway.
If they were to ask you on the board exam,
which of the following has a tram track appearance,
it's a giveaway that the answer would be membranoproliferative.
All right, so again, I use the name to help me
because I think it takes you very far
when you're considering many of the disorders in pathology.
Now unfortunately, we're not done.
When you have membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis,
it's actually divided into two types.
And it's divided into two types
based on the location of the deposits.
So let's illustrate this.
This is the endothelial cell.
That's sitting on top of a basement membrane.
And of course, the podocytes are sitting on the opposite side.
These are the epithelial cells.
In type one membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis,
you get deposits underneath the endothelial cell
or subendothelial.
So this would be type one.
And important to note that type one
is associated with hepatitis B virus
and hepatitis C virus infections.
That's particularly high yield.
Now in type one, it's also important to note,
and you should add this to the margin of your text,
that type one is more often associated
with the formation of tram tracts.
Okay, so type one, I would say a few things.
Number one, hepatitis B virus, hepatitis C virus,
and more often associated
with the formation of tram tracts.
In type two membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis,
you get deposition of the immune complexes
within the basement membrane.
So this is type two.
Now in type two,
there is a very super high yield association.
And that is that these patients have an antibody
in their blood called C3 nephritic factor.
Basically it's an autoantibody.
It's called C3 nephritic factor,
and it stabilizes C3 convertase.
Now the stabilization of C3 convertase
leads to the over-activation of complement,
which then results in inflammation,
and then can drive this process forward.
Now let me just hit home on this
in order to highlight this high yield point.
So remember that C3 is an important component of complement,
and C3 gets converted into C3A and C3B.
Now the enzyme that's going to cause this conversion
is called C3 convertase.
Remember that whenever you generate C3 convertase,
you very quickly destroy C3 convertase,
because you only want to turn complement on
for just a very, very limited period of time.
So normally C3 convertase would be destroyed rapidly.
However, in these patients with type two,
membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis,
they actually have an antibody that blocks C3 convertase
and stabilizes it.
Now it doesn't block the activity,
but it stabilizes it so it can't be broken down.
So when it can't be broken down,
this is going to result in over-activation of complement,
and so you're going to get a decreased serum C3
with an over-activation of complement.
That's going to result in inflammation
and inflammatory damage within the glomerulus.
Now with that in mind,
I'd like to highlight one more important point,
and that is membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis
can actually produce nephritic syndrome
or nephrotic syndrome or both.
Now I put it in this discussion here
because it fits well with the concept of membranous
and then thinking about membranoproliferative after that.
So I combined it here because it has the potential
to create nephrotic syndrome.
However, you should bear in mind
that it can also create nephritic syndrome,
or sometimes it can create both.
And of course, if you have over-activation of complement
as you would have in type two,
you're going to get inflammation within the glomerulus,
and that inflammation is going to be more
of a nephritic syndrome than it would be a nephrotic syndrome.
However, for the purposes of learning,
I think it's nice to put membranous glomerulonephropathy
sort of right before membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis.
Now another reason why I do it
is because it helps me to remember
that in the membranotype diseases,
whether it be membranous or membranoproliferative,
you're always going to have immune complex deposits,
and that those immune complex deposits
will be in one of three locations.
And the diseases together,
they cover every possible location.
What I mean by that is that here's the endothelial cell,
and then you've got the basement membrane,
and then on top of that you've got the podocyte, correct?
Now what can happen here is that you can get deposits
underneath the epithelium, that's called subepithelium,
and that's seen in membranous glomerulonephropathy.
And then you can also get deposits in this,
underneath the endothelium, and that's seen in type one,
membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis,
or you can get deposits within the basement membrane,
and that's seen in type two, membranoproliferative glomerulonephritis.
So notice that in these membranous type diseases,
there are, you covered all three layers, right?
There was one possibility of being
underneath the endothelial cell,
one possibility of being in the basement membrane,
and one possibility of being underneath the epithelial cell.
And so we covered all three.
One, two, and then membranous up here.
So all three were covered by these diseases.
And again, in all of these diseases, the key problem is immune complex,
so you're gonna get a granular immunofluorescence, et cetera, et cetera.
And so that's the way I like to think about these disorders.
In fact, the way I overall think about nephrotic syndrome
is that there's basically six causes,
and I put them together in twos.
So you've got minimal change disease and FSGS,
and in both of those disorders, the key problem is effacement of the foot process,
and then you've got membranous and membranoproliferative,
and in those two disorders, the key problem is deposition of immune complexes,
which is then going to give you granular immunofluorescence
and all the classic findings that we've described.
And then there's two more causes of nephrotic syndrome,
so there's six in all.
And the next two are going to be systemic diseases
that then affect the glomerulus to cause a nephrotic syndrome.
And so the first of those is diabetes mellitus.
Now what happens in diabetes is that you get a high serum glucose, obviously.
And the high serum glucose results in non-enzymatic glycosylation
of the vascular basement membrane.
Now when you stick sugar on the basement membrane
without the use of enzyme, that's called non-enzymatic glycosylation.
Of course, when that happens to the vascular basement membrane,
that's going to result in the basement membrane becoming leaky,
and so what's going to happen is that protein will leak into the wall
of the blood vessel, creating something called highline arteriolosclerosis.
And we talked about highline arteriolosclerosis in the vascular section,
and recall there, I told you that highline arteriolosclerosis
occurs with both hypertension, in particular benign hypertension, and diabetes.
Now when you get highline arteriolosclerosis,
the problem is that you get thickening of the blood vessel wall
with this protein-like material,
which then results in a decrease in the caliber of the lumen.
Now it's important to note that in diabetes, what actually happens
is that if this is the afferent arteriole, and here is the efferent arteriole,
you get preferential highline arteriolosclerosis in the efferent arteriole.
Now that's going to reduce the caliber of the lumen,
and creating an increased pressure in the glomerulus, right?
If you tighten this, there's going to be more back pressure here in the glomerulus.
That increased pressure in the glomerulus is going to create hyperfiltration,
which is going to initially begin as microalbuminuria,
but eventually you'll get sclerosis of the mesangium of the glomerulus,
and as you get sclerosis of the mesangium of the glomerulus,
it'll progress to nephrotic syndrome.
Now one of the important things to recognize concerning this pathogenesis
is that if you give patients ACE inhibitors,
you can actually slow the progression of the hyperfiltration injury.
And the reason is because angiotensin II also squeezes down here,
and so now that additional squeezing down
is only going to create additional hyperfiltration injury.
So if you can block angiotensin II,
you'll decrease some of that pressure at the efferent arteriole,
which will then decrease the hyperfiltration injury.
So let's read together what we say in the text.
In diabetes, you get high serum glucose
that leads to non-enzymatic glicosylation of the vascular basement membrane.
By the way, that's the very first change that occurs in the kidney.
Non-enzymatic glicosylation of the vascular basement membrane.
Sometimes examiners will ask you what's the first change.
This then results in highline arteriolosclerosis.
Of course, the efferent arteriole is preferentially affected,
leading to a high glomerular filtration pressure.
The high filtration pressure results in microalbuminuria.
This eventually progresses to nephrotic syndrome.
The hallmark of nephrotic syndrome would be
that you would see sclerosis of the mesangium,
and that sclerosis results in these classic nodules
called Kimmel-Steele-Wilson nodules.
And as I've mentioned, ACE inhibitors would slow the progression
of hyperfiltration-induced damage.
So here's a picture of the glomerulus.
Here's the round glomerulus here.
And notice that in the mesangium, you've got this dense sclerosis.
And of course, these are Kimmel-Steele-Wilson nodules.
There's a perfect one right here.
Very high yield, as this is pathognomonic for diabetes.
The last disorder that can create nephrotic syndrome
would be systemic amyloidosis.
Remember that when patients have systemic amyloidosis,
the kidney is the most commonly involved organ.
I told you that when we talked about amyloid.
The amyloid will deposit in the mesangium,
and that will result in a nephrotic syndrome.
Of course, a biopsy would show Congo red staining
with apple green birefringents under polarized light.
Now basically, in summary, we've done the nephrotic syndromes,
but just remember there are six nephrotic syndromes,
and study them in pairs.
Minimal change disease, FSGS.
Membranous, membranoproliferative.
And then diabetes, and amyloid.
And so in each of these, again, you have some common themes.
And I think if you understand nephrotic syndrome in this way,
you'll be very strong in this topic.
That concludes our discussion of nephrotic syndrome.